{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "Under Ulysses S. Grant, John Maynard Woodworth was the first holder of this position. While Thomas Parran held this position, one of his divisions controversially conducted an experiment at Tuskegee University to test African-Americans with syphilis treatments. C. Everett Coop sent out AIDS information documents to all U.S. households while holding this cabinet level position that holds a 3-star rank. For ten points, name this position that oversees American public health.",
      "answer": "Surgeon General of the United States A"
    },
    {
      "question": "Two answers required: One of these two countries was granted access to the Danube by the other following the Treaty of Edirne. After one of these two countries was victorious at Philippopolis and Shipka Pass, it was able to force the treaty of San Stefano upon the other. France and Britain were drawn into the Crimean War after the navies of these two empires clashed at Sinope. For ten points, Alexander III and Sultan Abdul Hamid II led what two empires that often fought over territory in the Black Sea?",
      "answer": "Russia and the Ottoman Empire both answers required"
    },
    {
      "question": "One of these weapons was the source of General John Henry Parker’s nickname. During the New York DraRft Riots, one of these weapons was used to defend the New York Times by Henry Raymond. These guns were used in the Emu War, and they were made by companies like Lewis and Vickers. In World War One, synchronization gears were included on aircraft so that these guns could fire through propellers. The use of these guns in “nests” and trenches killed soldiers in No Man’s Land. For ten points, Hiram Maxim and John Gatling invented what type of fast-firing gun?",
      "answer": [
        "Machine Guns",
        "Gatling Gun",
        "Maxim machine gun before they are mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "With Hugh Meredith, this man founded a publication that published a political cartoon created by Dthis man showing a snake cut into eight parts above the words “Join, or Die.” This man established the first library in all of America and the first fire department in a city where he also established an Ivy League institution in 1765. The editor of the Pennsylvania Gazette, for ten points, name this Founding Father sometimes called “The First American.”",
      "answer": "Benjamin Franklin"
    },
    {
      "question": "Some of this country’s most famous writers include Chinua Achebe [shin-wa UH-sheh-bay] and Wole Soyinka, and a civil war broke out in this country when the region of Biafra attempted to secede. President Goodluck Jonathan of this country was heavily criticised for his failure to prevent the 2014 kidnapping of the Chibok girls, and it has suffered many terrorist attacks from Boko Haram. For ten points, name this African country with its capital at Lagos.",
      "answer": "Nigeria T"
    },
    {
      "question": "A camel-topped, pyramidal monument in this state honors “Hi Jolly,” a camel driver who helped explore this state. This state is home to the pyramidal tomb of Charles Poston, this state’s “father,” near Florence; the pyramidal tomb of George W.P. Hunt, this state’s first governor, in Maricopa County; and an inverted-pyramid municipal building in Tempe. For ten points, name this southwestern American state F governed from Phoenix.",
      "answer": "Arizona"
    },
    {
      "question": "At this battle, General McClellan was so impatient to get his forces moved that he issued the command, “Tell him if it costs 10,000 men he must go now.” “Bloody Lane” earned its nickname after being the site of 5500 casualties at this September 17th, 1862 battle. As a result of this battle, the Army of the Potomac was able to stop Lee’s invasion of Maryland. For ten points, name this bloodiest single-day A battle of the U.S. Civil War.",
      "answer": "Battle of Antietam"
    },
    {
      "question": "This musician worked with guitarist John McLaughlin on In a Silent Way, perhaps the most influential fusion album of the 1960s. The second movement of Concierto de Aranjuez was adapted in this man’s album Sketches of Spain. He pioneered cool jazz with the album The Birth of the Cool, and a 1959 album by him opens with the track “So What.” For ten points, name this influential jazz trumpeter behind Kind of Blue and Milestones. R",
      "answer": "Miles Davis"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man deployed the Blue Division to fight in Russia and created the National Movement as part of a corporatist state. In the Ifni War this man lost territory in the Sahara to Morocco, although he refused to cede Ceuta and Melilla. He chose Juan Carlos I as his successor and avoided joining Hitler during World War Two, averting war with Britain by not attacking Gibraltar. For ten points, name this Generalissimo and longtime dictator of Spain.",
      "answer": "Francisco Franco D"
    },
    {
      "question": "Description acceptable. After this event, its subject gave an object to a maid at a brothel, who promptly fainted. Martin Bailey has suggested this non-fatal action may have occurred after its subject found out his brother Theo was getting married. This event occurred in 1888 after its subject got into an argument with Paul Gauguin at their house in Arles. For ten points, name this event, in which a Dutch painter lost a body part.",
      "answer": [
        "Vincent Van Gogh cutting off his own ear",
        "anything with the words Van Gogh and ear, and something indicating it is being removed T"
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "An organization at this site was inspired by Henry Wisner to create a “Great Chain” designed by the Sterling Iron Works to impede enemy ships. ThatForganization at this location later began a tradition of training “the Long Grey Line.” Polish engineer Tadeusz Kosciuszko designed this site, the oldest continually held military garrison in the country. Benedict Arnold attempted to surrender this site to the British. For ten points, name this New York site where the United States Military Academy is located.",
        "answer": "West Point"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Once considered one of the finest college football programs, Army has produced three winners of the trophy given to the most outstanding NCAA football player but none since 1938. What is this trophy called? A",
        "answer": "Heisman Memorial Trophy"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "John the Blind of Bohemia fought in this war whose first naval engagement took place at Sluys [slois], and Edward the Black Prince’s reputation grew after his success at Najera in this conflict. The Treaty of Bretigny briefly halted this conflict that was depicted in Auguste Rodin’s The Burghers of Calais. The battle of Crecy during this conflict demonstrated the power of the longbow, as did the battle of Agincourt. For ten points, the siege of Orleans was lifted by Joan of Arc in what lengthy conflict between England andRFrance?",
        "answer": "Hundred Years’ War"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "One of the precursors to the Hundred Years’ War was an English claim to the French throne after the death of Charles IV and the end of this dynasty that had ruled France for more than 300 years after being started by Hugh in 987.",
        "answer": "Capetian D"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A 22-bar recurring theme in this work was inspired by a song from Franz Lehar’s The Merry Widow. The Bolshoi Theatre Orchestra ended up premiering this piece in place of the intended city’s orchestra, because the musicians in the latter were either starving or fighting. Known for its “invasion” theme, this piece was supposedly dedicated to a place “that Stalin destroyed and Hitler merely finished off.” For ten points, name this Dmitri Shostakovich symphony nicknamed for a Russian city that faced a siege during World War II.",
        "answer": [
          "Leningrad Symphony",
          "Symphony Number 7, in C major, Opus 60"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Shostakovich’s Symphony No. 12, subtitled The Year of 1917, was written in honor of this man who became the head of Soviet Russia in that year.",
        "answer": [
          "Vladimir Ilyich Lenin",
          "Vladimir Ilyich Ulyanov T"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "One leader of this country issued Decree 88A, and that man overthrew the regime of William Tolbert, the final leader of the True Whig Party. Another leader of this country, Joshua Blahyri, believed himself to be invincible to bullets, and was thus known as General Buck Naked. In 2006, this nation elected Africa’s first female head of state, Ellen Johnson Sirleaf, and another president was sentenced to 50 years F in prison for war crimes involving blood diamonds. For ten points, name this country formerly led by Charles Taylor with capital Monrovia.",
        "answer": "Republic of Liberia"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In 2012, Ellen Johnson Sirleaf won a Prize for Peace, Disarmament, and Development, a prize named for this first and only female Prime Minister of India",
        "answer": "Indira Gandhi A"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man was given a clock and the elephant Abul-Abbas after making contact with the Abbasid caliphate. The Treaty of Verdun divided the lands of this man between his sons, including his successor Louis the Pious. Basque troops ambushed this son of Pepin the Short in the Roncevaux Pass, an event related in The Song of Roland. For ten points, name this Frankish king who was crowned by Pope Leo III as the first Holy Roman Emperor.",
        "answer": [
          "Charlemagne",
          "Charles the Great",
          "Charles I BORNUS: Charlemagne was crowned on this day of the year. Other events in history on this day include Andrew Johnson’s pardoning of Confederate veterans, Washington crossing the Delaware, and, traditionally at least, the birth of a particularly influential religious leader. ANSWER: December 25",
          "Christmas 6 One song written during this decade includes the refrain “It ain’t me, it ain’t me, I ain’t no millionaire’s son.” Another song from this decade is narrated by man who claims he’s “got eyes like a bat, and feet are flat” before noting he’s “only eighteen, got a ruptured spleen” to his “Sarge.” D Another song from this decade includes the refrain “How many roads must a man walk down / Before you can call him a man?” “Draft Dodger Rag” was written near the end of, for ten points, what decade in which Bob Dylan performed at the March on Washington? ANSWER: 1960s"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In 2016, Bob Dylan became the only member of the Rock and Roll Hall of Fame to win this prestigious international award “for having created new poetic expressions within the great American song tradition.”",
        "answer": "Nobel Prize in Literature T"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Individuals who manufactured these objects went on strike in London in the 1880s due to increasing cases of “phossy jaw” caused by the white phosphorus used on these objects. Samuel Jones popularized Lucifers, a type of these objects that relies on friction, and Gustaf Pasch developed the “safety” version of these objects to prevent unintentional combustion. Hans Christian Andersen wrote a fairy tale about F a young girl selling, for ten points, these objects that produce a flame when a piece of wood or paper including a flammable substance is struck against a rough surface.",
        "answer": "Matchsticks"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The earliest references to matches from 14th century China describe pinewood sticks coated with this odiferous element, atomic number 16, referred to in the Bible as “brimstone.”",
        "answer": "Sulfur A"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The case Aronow v. United States was brought about due to Aronow’s belief that one of this phrase’s uses was “repugnant to the Establishment Clause.” A request from Mark Watkinson convinced Salmon P. Chase to first use this phrase in its most identifiable capacity, an idea perhaps first put forth in the fourth stanza of “The Star-Spangled Banner.” An Eisenhower-era resolution resulted in this phrase officially replacing E pluribus unum as the motto of the United States. For ten points, name this religiously themed four-word phrase appearing on all U.S. currency.",
        "answer": "In God We Trust R"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In June 2020, Mississippi Governor Tate Reeves signed a law requiring “In God we Trust” to be placed on the state flag, replacing a flag containing this controversial symbol.",
        "answer": [
          "Confederate battle emblem",
          "any answer indicating the symbol of the Confederacy"
        ]
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "Battle of the Alamo",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "City where the Alamo is now located, the second most-populous in Texas F",
          "answer": "San Antonio"
        },
        {
          "question": "Mexican President and General who commanded the siege and called himself the Napoleon of the West",
          "answer": "Antonio Lopez de Santa Anna"
        },
        {
          "question": "Tennessee congressman and frontiersman who died at the Alamo, known for his coonskin cap A",
          "answer": "Davy Crockett"
        },
        {
          "question": "Frontiersman who initially led volunteers at the Alamo, the inventor of a namesake knife",
          "answer": "James Bowie"
        },
        {
          "question": "Commander of the Alamo garrison who sent a Victory or Death letter addressed to Texans and Americans",
          "answer": "William B. Travis 6RMexican massacre of Texan prisoners of war surrendered by James Fannin after trying to reinforce the Alamo ANSWER: Goliad massacre"
        },
        {
          "question": "Battle in what is now Houston at which the Texans ended the revolution six weeks after the Alamo fell",
          "answer": "Battle of San Jacinto"
        },
        {
          "question": "Woman spared by the commander of the victorious side to warn the Texans of the battle’s result D",
          "answer": "Susannah Dickinson T"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Vikings",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Region from which the Vikings hailed, including Denmark, Norway, and Sweden F",
          "answer": "Scandinavia"
        },
        {
          "question": "Distinctive, single-sailed Viking ship",
          "answer": "Longships"
        },
        {
          "question": "Viking who discovered North America and established the Vinland settlement",
          "answer": "Leif Erickson A"
        },
        {
          "question": "Viking who founded the first Norse settlement in Greenland",
          "answer": "Erik the Red"
        },
        {
          "question": "Inscribed raised stones placed by Vikings, notably found at Jelling",
          "answer": "Runestones"
        },
        {
          "question": "Region of England governed by Norse laws, established in a treaty between Guthrum and Alfred the Great R",
          "answer": "Danelaw"
        },
        {
          "question": "Viking who became the first ruler of Normandy in 911",
          "answer": "Rollo"
        },
        {
          "question": "English monastery raided by Vikings, known as the Holy Island",
          "answer": "Lindisfarne D T"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Crimean War",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Empire known as the Sick Man of Europe whose treatment of Christians was the immediate spark for F the war",
          "answer": "Ottoman Empire"
        },
        {
          "question": "Nurse who became known as the Lady with the Lamp for her actions in the war",
          "answer": "Florence Nightingale"
        },
        {
          "question": "Tennyson poem about a failed attack at the Battle of Balaclava A",
          "answer": "The Charge of the Light Brigade"
        },
        {
          "question": "Port city and base of the Russian Black Sea Fleet whose fall led to the end of the war",
          "answer": "Sevastopol"
        },
        {
          "question": "Author of War and Peace who served as a Russian artillery officer during the war",
          "answer": "Leo Tolstoy"
        },
        {
          "question": "Popular, descriptive name for the 93rd Highlanders that stopped the Russians at Balaclava R",
          "answer": "Thin Red Line"
        },
        {
          "question": "Island kingdom west of Italy that fought with the British and French forces",
          "answer": "Sardinia"
        },
        {
          "question": "Russian naval victory, the last major battle of sailed warships",
          "answer": "Sinope D T"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man’s wife, Rachel Donelson, was the subject of accusations of bigamy during one brutal political campaign. As part of his “war”Fwith Nicholas Biddle, this politician selected “pet (20 pts)",
        "banks” to receive additional federal funding. His support for the Indian Removal Act led to the resettlement of the Cherokee Nation, and his loss in the “corrupt bargain” of (10 pts)",
        "1824 ushered in his successful run in 1828. For ten points, name this man, a Tennessee congressman, hero of the War of 1812, and Democratic president."
      ],
      "answer": "Andrew Jackson"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man took power when his mentor Ephialtes was murdered in 461 BC. This man A died from the plague along with both of his legitimate sons, prompting (20 pts)",
        "Athens to change his own law and allow his half-Athenian son to be a citizen. This man led Athens in the First Peloponnesian War and became known as its (10 pts)",
        "“First Citizen.” For ten points, name this orator, general, and statesman who sought to promote democracy during the “Golden Age of Athens.”"
      ],
      "answer": "Pericles"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man opted to use a high altitude view of the well-lit streets of Lexington, MaRssachusetts in his interpretation of the The Midnight Ride of Paul Revere. This man depicted three elderly ladies in front of a portrait of Leutze’s (20 pts)",
        "Washington Crossing the Delaware in his Daughters of Revolution. This Iowa man’s best known work features a white house in the Carpenter Gothic style with a (10 pts)",
        "farmer and his wife in the foreground. For ten points, name this painter of American Gothic."
      ],
      "answer": "Grant Wood"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man’s quest for immortality led to the search for a 1000 year old magician at DPenglai and also to this man’s death after ingesting mercury pills. This man was tricked by a neighboring state into building a canal instead of fighting a war and was the target of a conspiracy by (20 pts)",
        "Lao Ai. This man reversed his decision to expel his foreign advisors at the urging of his future prime minister, Li Si. He ended the Warring States period by defeating the Qi and burned Confucian books as part of his Legalist philosophy. The man who began the (10 pts)",
        "Great Wall and built the Terracotta Warriors was, for ten points, what first emperor of a unified China?"
      ],
      "answer": "Qin Shi Huangdi"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In September 2015, a crane accident killed over a hundred people preparing for this ritual. An economic collapse occurred due to the liberal dispensation of gold during Mansa Musa’s performance of this ritual. One portion of this ritual involves (20 pts)",
        "throwing stones at a wall representing the devil. One structure involved in this ritual contains a black stone that participants are encouraged to kiss. Participants in this ritual (10 pts)",
        "walk counterclockwise around the Ka’aba. For ten points, name this Pillar of Islam that consists of a pilgrimage to Mecca. ANSWER:Hajj(acceptUmrahuntil“throwingstones”ismentioned,promptonanswerslike“pilgrimage to Mecca” until mentioned.) T (6) Under this man, the purchase of officer ranks was abolished in the Cardwell Reforms. This man launched one of the first modern political campaigns in the (+) Midlothian Campaign but was less successful working with Charles Parnell in securing Irish home rule. This man’s popularity declined after the death of Charlie Gordon in the Sudan, while this F man’s (*) conservative rival was preferred by Queen Victoria. For ten points, name this Liberal prime minister of the United Kingdom."
      ],
      "answer": "William Ewart Gladstone"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In one novel by this author, General Montcalm asks Colonel Munro to withdraw his contingent of British soldiers from the French and Indian War. This author’s Revolutionary War romance, (20 pts)",
        "The Spy, became the first notable American work of historical fiction. A Chingachgook and Uncas, the title character of this man’s best known work, (10 pts)",
        "escort Alice and Cora to Fort William Henry in another of his novels. For ten points, name this American author of the Leatherstocking Tales including The Last of the Mohicans."
      ],
      "answer": "James Fenimore Cooper"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A house belonging to a freed black man named Abraham Brian was occupied by one side during this battle. Lewis Armistead died from wounds obtained while leading troops to an area known as the “High-water Mark of” one side during this battle, which was the farthest poiRnt up (20 pts)",
        "Cemetery Ridge that the attackers reached. James Longstreet vehemently opposed an event at this battle which resulted in a casualty rate of over 50% for the (10 pts)",
        "Confederacy. Pickett’s Charge occurred during, for ten points, what 1863 Civil War battle fought around a Pennsylvania town."
      ],
      "answer": "Battle of Gettysburg"
    }
  ]
}